My wife attends Catholic Church.
We both attended
Catholic Church in the past.
But at some point
I realized it wasn't for me
and stopped attending many years ago.
I remained non-religious for a while
but became interested in Buddhism.
Although they aren't
official Buddhist scriptures,
I've been finding comfort in reading books
by Zen priests at times of difficulty.
I've felt more at peace and am now
strongly drawn towards Buddhist faith.
When I go to the mountains,
I stop at a temple to offer 108 bows.
I recently even completed 3,000 bows.
Lately my wife found out about this.
Since then, she stubbornly
refuses to talk to me.
She claims that it would be
difficult to maintain a marriage
with a person of Buddhist faith.
I've tried convincing her that
religious beliefs should be respected.
But as Christians tend to be exclusive,
she won't accept my point of view.
Ironically my wife had no religion
when we got married.
I initially persuaded her
to go to church with me.
And now that I go to Buddhist temples
instead of church,
she seems to feel betrayed.
As Christians tend to be exclusive,
my wife is stubbornly
refusing to talk about it.
My wife doesn't expect me
to return to Catholic church.
She requests that
I at least remain free of religion
for the sake of our family.
I told her that Buddhism
is the essence of who I am,
hence renouncing my values
would mean losing myself.
No matter what I say,
she won't understand.
So it's really difficult.
Are you subservient to her?
(Audience Laughter)
Religious differences aside, are you
generally subservient to your wife?
(Questioner) It's not like that.
(Sunim) I'm just asking.
Are you subservient to her or not?
(Questioner) I'm not.
If not, you don't have an issue.
If you are subservient,
it would be a problem.
But if you are not,
your problem isn't difficult to resolve.
In other words, if you are
in an equal relationship with her,
or better yet in a slightly
dominant position,
you can make up to her through
other things aside from religion.
I've been married to her for 25 years,
so I know her personality well.
She's very headstrong and stubborn
once she makes up her mind.
She doesn't have a gentle,
understanding personality.
You chose to marry her.
What can you do about that?
(Questioner)
That's why I'm here.
I can't seem to find a solution myself
no matter how hard I try.
Is your wife passionate
and actively involved
in church activities on a daily basis?
She isn't completely obsessed with church,
but she's quite serious about it.
Given you weren't raised a Buddhist
and had once attended church,
it may seem to her that you're obsessed
with Buddhism. Can this be the case?
I don't think so.
She has seen me reading
Buddhism related books though.
Then you should explain to her
that unlike Christianity,
Buddhism is a philosophy
and a study of the mind.
Try recommending her things
to read for fun.
(Questioner)
That won't work.
She fundamentally rejects
Buddhism altogether.
Even if she resists, you can say
"I'm not changing my religion.
I'm studying Buddhism
out of academic interest."
Instead of saying
"I want to be a Buddhist",
you can say "I went hiking and passed by
a nice and serene temple, so I bowed."
You might be acting too obvious.
I haven't been too obvious.
It's just that given
I do believe in Buddhism,
I can't lie about it.
I told her I won't be upfront about
my beliefs, but she still refuses.
So I'm at a loss.
Is she asking for a divorce
because of this?
She's not, but she insists that I should
at least return to having no faith
in order to maintain
a normal relationship.
What does she mean
by a normal relationship?
Is she refusing to sleep with you?
(Sunim)
Is she using that as a weapon?
No, it's not that. We're not even
conversing at the moment.
So now...
If you can't talk to her,
think of it this way.
Don't be too anxious to talk to her.
Leave her alone
if she doesn't want to talk to you.
Don't get frustrated over it.
Why get frustrated over
this as a person who's practicing?
Even if she's not talking to you,
treat her with ease and comfort.
If she asks anything, always respond.
If she doesn't want to be bothered,
leave her alone and
focus on cultivating yourself
Silent meditation is an important practice
Hence you can practice silent meditation.
It seems like you're not understanding
the situation from a Buddhist perspective.
Once you do, there is no problem.
Just say "Yes, honey, you are right.
I'm sorry". Don't be too obvious.
I am not obvious about my faith
when I'm home.
But I think I must have shared my address
with a Buddhist organization once.
A letter was sent home.
One day I got home from work
and my wife says,
"I received this letter,
and I tossed it out."
I'm not saying you should lie.
You can say, "Ah, I must have left
our address on a guestbook
at a temple while hiking."
I understand.
So should I give it more time?
It's not about giving it more time.
You should be at peace yourself
in order to understand your wife.
You should think to yourself,
'She must have felt disappointed that
I insisted we go to church,
and now I go to temples instead.'
'My wife tends to commit to things, so
of course my actions would've upset her.'
Try to empathize with her.
When she complains, tell her
"I understand how you feel.
Don't worry too much though.
I'm just growing old and getting curious.
I want to study different things and am
finding myself interested in these books."
"It's not a matter of religion
like you think it is.
Zen masters don't ever say
believe in a god."
"They never ask to believe in Buddhism.
I'm just studying it for the sake
for studying, so no need to worry."
Make an effort
to improve your relationship.
Do the dishes for her
if you haven't been.
If you change for the better
while going to temples,
she won't consider religious differences
as a problem.
If you don't change for the better,
then it becomes a problem.
Hence I asked earlier on who the dominant
person is in your relationship.
If you're the dominant person, you should
give up your rights and be nicer to her.
If you're the subservient person,
being nicer may seem servile.
(Audience Laughter)
Your spouse may look down on you
even more, hence I asked.
If you are on equal footing,
you can accommodate to your wife
areas beside religion.
Empathize with her more
when she speaks, be accepting.
If you do that, your wife will notice
the positive changes in you.
If she ever mentions, "Hmm, I think
you're acting different these days",
you can say,
"Really? I don't know.
I've been reading books on
Buddhism and Zen masters."
"I realize that all my life
I've been living single-minded."
"Life is short, I shouldn't have been
insisting on things too much.
I've been reflecting on myself,
maybe that's changed me."
You should continue talking
to her this way.
If your wife argues with you
over going to temple today,
say you are sorry.
If she's surprised
by your unexpected response,
say "The monk told me
that marriage is most important,
hence I shouldn't be obsessing over
religion too much."
"He told me
to put religion behind marriage"
This will show her that I'm on her side.
Hence she may think to herself that
the monk isn't all that bad after all.
(Audience Laughter)
Empathize with her this way
and slowly start talking to her.
There is no need to say she should
believe in Buddhism because you do.
If your attitude in life becomes
more composed,
understanding and tolerant,
your wife will naturally become
accepting of your ways.
You'll face conflict at first
as she won't get things her way.
But no matter how hard
she resists and complains,
smile and say,
"I understand. Yes, I will do as you say."
"Don't worry too much,
I'm just studying that's all."
As time goes by,
she will come around and accept things.
She may even become curious
and ask about things.
So take a long term perspective.
Don't try to find a quick fix for it.
(Questioner)
Yes, I will do that.
(Applause)